Finding Aid for Episcopal Church. Diocese of Michigan records, 1830-2001
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Bishops' files
  - Bishop Archie Crowley files 1954-1972
    - W clergy (Box 33)
    - Zambia (Box 33)
- Executive and administrative bodies
  The Executive and administrative bodies series contains files of the central boards of the diocese, including the Board of Trustees, Executive Council, Standing Committee, and Commission on Ministry. Since 1920 the executive council (since 1995 called diocesan council) has met between diocesan conventions to continue its policy-making role. The standing committee provides advice and counsel for the bishop. Since 1875 the trustees of the diocese have managed the diocesan assets.
  - Board of Trustees
    - "History of the trustees" and "A record of the funds held" written by Bess Wormley 1965 (Box 3)
    - History of the trustees... additional pages 1966-1977 (Box 3)
    - Minute book 1875-1935 (Box 3)
    - Minute book 1935-1958 (Box 3)
    - Financial Journal 1924-1931 (Box 3)
    - Episcopal Funds ledgers 1885-1923, 2 volumes (Box 3)
    - Minutes 1959-1980 (Box 34)
    - Minutes 1977-1989 (Box 34)
    - Minutes 1989-2001 (Box 34)
    - Correspondence, etc., binder 1982 (Box 35)
    - Correspondence, etc., binder 1982-1984 (Box 35)
    - Correspondence, etc., binder 1985-1988 (Box 35)
    - Correspondence, etc., binder 1990-1991 (Box 35)
    - Centennial Fund and Reinforcement Fund record book 1927-1959, 1 folders; 1 volumes (Box 4)
    - Annual Reports 1963-1981 (some lacking), 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Finance Committee minutes 1966-1971 (Box 4)
    - Diocesan Development Fund (Box 4)
    - Closed estates (Box 4)
    - Bishop Page Foundation (Box 4)
    - Miscellanea (Box 4)
  - Executive Council
    - Minute books 1920-1971 (Box 25)
    - Volumes containing meeting packets 1966-1975, 5 volumes (Box 26)
    - Volumes containing meeting packets 1976-September 1980 (Box 27)
    - Record book of Executive Council departments 1920-1922 (Box 28)
    - Minute books of Executive Council and Departments 1922-1945, 6 volumes (Box 28)
    - Minute books of Executive Council and Departments 1946-1963, 9 folders (Box 29)
    - Record books of diocese staff members W. G. Lonergan and Eileen Witzky containing minutes and other materials from meetings of the Executive Council (Box 30)
    - Program Committee and Executive Council Minutes December 1965-February 1967 (Box 30)
    - Goals and priorities / planning and evaluation working papers (Box 30)
    - Diocesan Committee for Missions 1972-1973 handbook (Box 30)
    - Diocesan Reference Book (Box 30)
  - Standing Committee
    - Record books 1833-1923, 1946-1963, 6 volumes (Box 6)
    - Meeting minutes 1925-1946, 4 folders (Box 6)
    - Meeting minutes 1950-1969, 4 folders (Box 31)
    - Meeting minutes 1972-1996, 11 volumes (Box 31)
  - Commission on Ministry
    - Meeting minutes 1972-1992, 7 volumes (Box 31)
- Diocesan organizations
  Other diocesan bodies with administrative or program responsibilities are represented in the Diocesan organizations series. Among others, this includes the Church Club, which was a group of churchmen who acted as support for diocesan projects and for the church office; and the Church Association of Michigan, which was formed to assist church authorities in the administration of temporal affairs such as trust, bequests, and titles.
  - Church Association of Michigan
    - Journal 1880-1908 (Box 7)
    - Letters 1880-1901, 4 volumes (Box 7)
    - Records of the Acts and Transactions 1880-1909 (Box 7)
    - Various papers 1879-1927 (Box 7)
  - Church Club and church clubs
    - Minutes 1908-1932, 5 volumes (Box 5)
    - Church clubs records 1915-1928, 2 volumes (Box 5)
      (include committee reports and minutes)
  - St. Christopher's House (Detroit inner-city mission)
    - Articles of incorporation; building plans (Box 32)
    - By-laws; board members (Box 32)
    - Concert materials (Box 32)
    - Correspondence (Box 32)
    - Director's reports (Box 32)
    - Financial reports (Box 32)
    - Minutes (Box 32)
    - Working files (Box 32)
  - Woman's Auxiliary
    - Minute Books 1880-1921, 8 volumes (Box 20)
  - Miscellaneous record books and papers
    The subseries of Miscellaneous record books and papers contains minutes of the diocesan convocations, record books listing ordinations, confirmations, and listings of dismissed clergy, and financial and assessment ledgers.
    - Aged and Infirm Clergy Ledger 1884-1918, 1 volumes (Box 8)
    - Aldrich, Bishop (clippings about consecration) (Box 8)
    - Architectural drawings and site plans of church buildings 1920s (Box 8)
    - Bishop Williams Memorial Fund Ledger 1923-1924, 1927, 1 volumes (Box 8)
    - Convocations/archdeaconry
      - Convocations -- General (Box 8)
      - Central Convocation minutes 1894-1916, 1 volumes (Box 8)
      - Northern Convocation minutes 1905-1915, 1 volumes (Box 8)
      - Southern Convocation/archdeaconry minutes 1894-1922, 2 volumes (Box 8)
      - Southwest Convocation 1973-1979 (Box 8)
    - Sayres, Rev. W. S. Registers of baptisms, marriages, burials and confirmations 1903-1914, 2 volumes (Box 8)
    - Treasurer's record books
      - 1842-1856 (Box 8)
      - 1897-1913 (Box 8)
      - 1913-1925 (Box 8)
    - Visitation book of the general missionary 1900-1908, 1 volumes (Box 8)
    - Confirmation record book January-April 1890 (Volume 1)
    - Confirmation record book 1906-1919, 1 volumes (Box 9)
    - Ordinations, confirmations and dismissals of clergy 1878-1892, 1 volumes (Box 9)
    - Lists of clergy, churches, missions and general information 1879-1905, 1 volumes (Box 9)
    - Clergy Newsletter, 1974-1984, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - General and miscellaneous (Box 9)
    - Volume containing affirmation by clergy of episcopal doctrine 1908-1942 (Box 9)
    - Golden Book of Remembrance, Woman's Auxiliary 1880-1930 (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous Papers and Notebooks
    - Typescript of diary (undated and writer unknown, but perhaps H. Henry Spoer) of mission trip to the Far East (294 pp.) (Box 14)
    - Notebook 1923-1925 of H. Henry Spoer containing and memoranda and reports regarding the work of the church among the foreign-born (Box 14)
    - Notebook circa 1923-1938 probably maintained by Charles O. Ford and containing minutes and reports of various special committees and commissions within the diocese (Box 14)
    - Notebook 1975-1983 re Combined Episcopal Service Appeals Committee of the Diocese of Michigan (Box 14)
    - Papers 1946 re election of the Rev. Richard Emrich to be suffragan bishop of the Diocese of Michigan (Box 14)
    - Papers 1946 re ordination and consecration for Richard Emrich (Box 14)
    - Papers 1982-1983 re 150th anniversary celebration of the Diocese of Michigan, 1 folders (Box 14)
    - Saginaw Urban Ministry Proposal 1973-1976, 1 folders (Box 14)
    - Mission Committee appointments 1920s-1940s (Box 14)
      (arranged by church)
    - Whitaker School of Theology
      - Faculty minutes 1957-1970, 2 folders (Box 14)
      - Brochures 2000s (Box 14)
    - Williams House brochure (Box 14)
    - Bishop Crowley retirement 1971 (Box 14)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 14)
- Diocesan programs
  At this time the series Diocesan programs contains records of only one program, Venture in Mission. From 1979 to 1988, the Diocese of Michigan was involved in a national Episcopal Church fund-raising drive sponsored by the national executive council. Given the name "Venture in Mission," this fund-raising activity in Michigan raised over 1.5 million dollars, half of which went to the national church headquarters, and half to local agencies involved in educational and ministerial outreach.
  - Venture in Mission
    - Correspondence
      - Distribution of Funds 1981 (Box 15)
      - General 1978-1987, 4 folders (Box 15)
    - Financial Information 1980-1985 (Box 15)
    - Follow-up Committee
      - Correspondence 1981-1985 (Box 15)
      - Memoranda 1981-1987, 2 folders (Box 15)
      - Reports 1981-1985 (Box 15)
    - Handbooks and Manuals (for congregations, clergy, etc.) (Box 15)
    - Internal Report--Status of Campaigns 1981 (Box 15)
    - Leadership Structure and Operational Plans (Box 15)
    - Local Congregations/Parishes--Statistics 1980 (Box 15)
    - Memoranda
      - [from] Tom Dunlap (assistant to bishop for financial support) 1978-1980 (Box 15)
      - [from] Peter Ramsey (VIM diocesan consultant) 1980-1981, 4 folders (Box 15)
      - [from] Oliver Reedy (VIM treasurer) 1980-1989 (Box 15)
      - General 1979-1985 (Box 15)
    - "News from Venture in Mission" (newsletter) 1981-1987 (incomplete) (Box 15)
    - Parish Education Task Force (Box 15)
    - Project Selection and Evaluation (Box 15)
    - Projects (from the file of William J. Logan, Archdeacon, Diocese of Michigan), 3 folders (Box 15)
    - Promotional/Educational Material, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Reports, Conventions, and Project Commitments 1980-1986 (Box 15)
    - "Some thoughts on the VIM Program" (treasurer's report) 1987 (Box 15)
    - Venture in Mission Bulletin (national) 1979 (Box 15)
    - Venture in Mission Committee minutes 1979 (Box 15)
- Diocesan staff
  The Diocesan staff series includes files of several staff members and offices
  - Archdeacon William Logan Files circa 1973-1984
    The Archdeacon William Logan Files subseries is comprised of two sub-subseries. One of these is arranged alphabetically by name of city and includes correspondence of the archdeacon with the individual church's leadership. There is also a scattering of historical sketches and clippings. The second sub-subseries is a topical file on various subjects from the period of the 1960s and 1970s.
    - Church files (files include correspondence, historical sketches, issues within individual churches; alphabetical by city)
      - Adrian (Box 10)
      - Algonac (Box 10)
      - Ann Arbor, 5 folders (Box 10)
      - Brighton (Box 10)
      - Brooklyn (Box 10)
      - Cambridge (Box 10)
      - Chelsea (Box 10)
      - Clarkston (Box 10)
      - Clinton (Box 10)
      - Croswell/Lexington (Box 10)
      - Dexter (Box 10)
      - DeWitt (Box 10)
      - Drayton Plains (Box 10)
      - East Lansing (Box 10)
      - Fairhaven (Box 10)
      - Forester (Box 10)
      - Hamburg (Box 10)
      - Harsen's Island, 2 folders (Box 10)
      - Higgins Lake/Houghton Lake (Box 10)
      - Hillsdale (Box 11)
      - Howell (Box 11)
      - Jackson -- St. Paul's (Box 11)
      - Jackson, Northwest -- St. Andrew's (Box 11)
      - Jonesville (Box 11)
      - Lake Orion (Box 11)
      - Lansing, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - Marine City (Box 11)
      - Marysville (Box 11)
      - Mason (Box 11)
      - Michigan Center (Box 11)
      - Milford (Box 11)
      - Oxford/Lake Orion, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - [P through V were not received] (Box 11)
      - Williamston, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - Ypsilanti (Box 11)
    - Topical Files 1960-1985
      - Architectural Commission 1978-1985 (Box 11)
      - Conference Centers 1977-1983 (Box 11)
      - Church Music 1977, 1979 (Box 11)
      - Cults (Box 11)
      - Elections
        - General (Box 11)
        - Fair Election Practices Commission 1960 (Box 11)
        - Michigan Fair Campaign Practices Committee 1979-1982, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - Episcopal Ministry at Michigan State University 1982 (Box 11)
      - Homosexuality 1977, 1972 (Box 11)
      - Medical Treatment Act 1977-1979 (Box 11)
      - Parochial Report Forms (Box 11)
      - Presiding Bishop's Fund for World Relief 1981-1983 (Box 11)
      - St. Luke's Episcopal Home 1972, 1978 (Box 11)
  - W. Gerald Lonergan files
    The W. Gerald Lonergan subseries documents the work of the Program Department, concerned with Christian Education and social action, and the diocese's interaction with the wider society and higher education, from about 1966 to 1974.
    - Cathedral Chapter 1958-1978
      - Agendas, minutes 1974-1978, 2 folders (Box 39)
      - Blue Ribbon Committee (Box 39)
      - Building Fund (Box 39)
      - Cathedral and Diocesan House 1970-1971 (Box 39)
      - Correspondence 1974-1975 (Box 39)
      - Operating (Box 39)
      - Operating account 1976 (Box 39)
      - Repair to Cathedral and Diocesan Center 1974 (Box 39)
      - Roster, meeting notices 1976-1978 (Box 39)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 39)
    - Executive Council 1972-1978
      - Agendas, minutes 1976-1977 (Box 39)
      - Correspondence 1972-1974 (Box 39)
      - Data for roster 1974-1975 (Box 39)
      - Evaluation of overnight, Dec 1974 (Box 39)
      - Goals and priorities 1978 (Box 39)
      - Minutes 1976 (Box 39)
      - Overnight 1974 (Box 39)
      - Planning and program objective budgeting in the Diocese of Michigan (Box 39)
      - Rosters, meeting notices 1976-1978 (Box 39)
    - Special ministries 1949-1978
      - Parishfield (Box 39)
      - St. Anne's Mead, 3 folders (Box 39)
      - St. Peter's Home for Boys (Box 39)
      - Tannahill (Box 39)
      - Williams House, 2 folders (Box 39)
    - Program Dept. circa 1966-1974
      - Correspondence, 11 folders (Box 40)
      - Address lists and committees (Box 40)
      - A.B.M. (Box 40)
      - Action centers (Church and Synagogue Committee) (Box 40)
      - Anti-racism conference June 20, 1970 (Box 40)
      - Audio-visual workshop (Box 40)
      - Black manifesto (Box 40)
      - Black power (Box 40)
      - Bluewater Convocation-Peg Henry (Box 40)
      - Christian education job description-St. John's Royal Oak (Box 40)
      - Christian education workshop on lesson planning November 28, 1970 (Box 40)
      - Church-state (Box 40)
      - Coalition on Peaceful Integration (Box 40)
      - Committee on Religion and Race (Box 40)
      - Common Cause (Box 40)
      - Community organization, 2 folders (Box 40)
      - Crowley, Father-Clergy conference May 6, 1970 (Box 40)
      - Deane-Strategy planning (Racism), Camp Holiday (Box 40)
      - Detroit Transit Alternative (Box 40)
      - Diocesan training program (Box 40)
      - Draft counseling 1967-1970 (Box 40)
      - Ecology clergy conference (Box 40)
      - Ecumenical Associates, 2 folders (Box 40)
      - Ecumenism (Box 40)
      - Educational models (Box 40)
      - Episcopal Peace Fellowship (Box 40)
      - Episcopal Society for Cultural and Racial Unity (Box 40)
      - Equal Justice Council (Box 40)
      - Evaluation-Racism programs (Box 40)
      - Executive Council (Box 40)
      - Executive Council mission study 1968-1969 (Box 40)
      - The Fish (Box 41)
      - Gun control resolution (Box 41)
      - Highland Park St. Alban's (Box 41)
      - Howe, Ruel-Clergy conference 1969 (Box 41)
      - Inner city Christian education (Box 41)
      - Inter-Faith Centers for Racial Justice (Box 41)
      - Inter-Faith Centers for Racial Justice TV challenge (Box 41)
      - Inter-Faith Centers for Racial Justice-Tom Anthony, W. Clabuesch (Box 41)
      - Internal Security Act 1950 Repeal of Title II (Box 41)
      - International concerns (Box 41)
      - Jennings, Dick-In-parish sensitivity training weekend (Box 41)
      - Lansing legislative memos (Box 41)
      - Last week in Lansing subscription (Box 41)
      - Lawson, Peter-Clergy conference December 07-09, 1970 (Box 41)
      - Lay leaders (Box 41)
      - Leadership Development Committee (Box 41)
      - Leadership Training Institute, Province 5, Phase I 1968 (Box 41)
      - Legislative seminar 1971 (Box 41)
      - McArthur, Ohio, Change project (Box 41)
      - McGehee, Bishop (Box 41)
      - May Days 1967 (Box 41)
      - Mayor's Committee for Human Resources Development, 2 folders (Box 41)
      - Michigan Pastors' Conference 1971-1972 (Box 41)
      - Model Anti-Racism Conference 19 September 1970 (Box 41)
      - National priorities (Box 41)
      - New clergy training program, 3 folders (Box 41)
      - Open housing (Box 41)
      - Peace education (Box 41)
      - Political Action Advisory Council, 2 folders (Box 41)
      - Program (Box 41)
      - Program (Box 42)
      - Program agenda, 2 folders (Box 42)
      - Program Committee, 4 folders (Box 42)
      - Program notes (Box 42)
      - Program staff memoranda (Box 42)
      - Project Equality, 3 folders (Box 42)
      - Project Equality construction survey (Box 42)
      - Project Equality fact sheets and related stewardship information (Box 42)
      - Province V education (Box 42)
      - Racism (Box 42)
      - Racism Strategy and Review Committee, 2 folders (Box 42)
      - Religious Education Conference 1970 (Box 42)
      - Resolutions (Box 42)
      - Riewald Conference December 02-03, 1969 (Box 42)
      - Riewald Conference January 1971 (Box 42)
      - Riot-Detroit (Box 42)
      - St. Joseph's "Sinkavich Affair" (Box 42)
      - Sex education (Box 42)
      - Sex Education Committee (Box 42)
      - Social activities/mission 1970 (Box 42)
      - Social Mission Planning Area Committee, 2 folders (Box 42)
      - Sparrow, Nan (Box 42)
      - Special Ministries Committee 1973-1975 (Box 42)
      - State of Michigan Training Laboratory (Box 42)
      - Sterling, Bishop, retreat February 09-10, 1970 (Box 42)
      - Stop A.B.M. (Box 42)
      - Suburban action centers (Box 42)
      - Teacher training (Box 42)
      - Teacher training, Essex, Ont. 1969 Dobson (Box 42)
      - Teacher training, Inkster (Box 42)
      - Teacher Training Subcommittee (Box 42)
      - Town and country 1968 (Box 43)
      - Town and country April 15-17, 1969 (Box 43)
      - Town and country training (Box 43)
      - Training position paper (Box 43)
      - United Ministries in Higher Education (Box 43)
      - Urban Clergy Conference 29-30 September 1970 (Box 43)
      - Urban crisis, 2 folders (Box 43)
      - Urban problems (Box 43)
      - Urban renewal (Box 43)
      - Vietnam (Box 43)
      - Vietnam War (Box 43)
      - War and peace packet 1969 (Box 43)
      - Warnecke, Bishop, conference December 12-13, 1969 (Box 43)
      - Washington legislature (Box 43)
      - World affairs, diocesan committee (Box 43)
      - Youth-Jo Kelsey (Box 43)
  - Bertram White, Stewardship Dept. 1959-1964
    - Correspondence Canada (Box 43)
    - Correspondence foreign (Box 43)
    - Correspondence orders (Box 43)
    - Diocese of Alaska (Box 43)
    - Diocese of Albany (Box 43)
    - Diocese of Bethlehem (Box 43)
    - Diocese of California (Box 43)
    - Diocese of Chicago (Box 43)
    - Diocese of Connecticut (Box 43)
    - Diocese of Dallas (Box 43)
    - Diocese of East Carolina (Box 43)
    - Diocese of Erie (Box 43)
    - Diocese of Florida (Box 43)
    - Diocese of Georgia (Box 43)
    - Diocese of Hawaii (Box 43)
    - Diocese of Iowa (Box 43)
    - Diocese of Kansas (Box 43)
    - Diocese of Long Island (Box 43)
    - Diocese of Los Angeles (Box 43)
    - Diocese of Massachusetts (Box 43)
    - Diocese of Minnesota (Box 43)
    - Diocese of Missouri (Box 43)
    - Diocese of New Jersey (Box 43)
    - Diocese of North Carolina (Box 43)
    - Diocese of Northern Michigan (Box 43)
    - Diocese of Ohio (Box 43)
    - Diocese of Olympia (Box 43)
    - Diocese of Rhode Island (Box 43)
    - Diocese of South Carolina (Box 43)
    - Diocese of South Dakota (Box 43)
    - Diocese of South Florida (Box 43)
    - Diocese of Southern Virginia (Box 43)
    - Diocese of Southwestern Virginia (Box 43)
    - Diocese of Virginia (Box 43)
    - Diocese of West Texas (Box 43)
    - Diocese of Western Massachusetts (Box 43)
    - Diocese of Western Michigan (Box 43)
    - Diocese of Western New York (Box 43)
  - Office of The Record
    Created by the diocesan convention in 1951 The Record was to be "a newspaper for the person in the pew." The Record's first editors were Jake Chapin (1951-62) and F. Plummer (1963-62). The next editor, Bill Logan, started his position in 1972. After serving as managing editor, Harry Cook became editor in 1976. In the mid-70s, Bishop Coleman McGehee created an independent editorial broad. No longer requiring the bishop's approval The Record became a truly independent voice. Following Cook, were editors John Laycock (1980-1981), Lois Leonard (1981-85), Jeanie Wylie Kellermann (1986-91) and Herb Gunn (1991-present). During the early 1990s the diocese strengthened the paper's position, by reinstating The Records designation as the official newspaper of the diocese. In 1995, the newspaper's editorial board revised the bylaws, which resulted in a closer working relationship with the bishop and the diocese. The editorial board continued to maintain their oversight of The Record. The Office of the Record subseries is divided into two sub-subseries, Reference Materials and Photographs.
    - Reference Materials 1917, 1970-2001
      The Reference (1917, 1970-2001) sub-subseries contains information about the diocese's social programs, administrative functions, schools, and conventions. There are two issue-oriented files. The first concerns Latin American refugee issues and the second is Bishop McGehee's commentary on Nicaragua. The majority of the materials are reports, memorandums, correspondence, brochures, press releases, and newsletters. There are some photographs scattered though the series. The files in this subseries are arranged alphabetically.
      - Altar Guild Diocesan 1990-1991 (Box 17)
      - Bishop H. Colman McGehee, Jr. Economic Justice Fund, Diocese of Michigan Justice Commission 1991-2001 (Box 17)
      - Canterbury House, University of Michigan student ministry undated (Box 17)
      - Canterbury on the Lake, senior housing (formerly St. Luke's Hospital and Home) 1917, 1972, 1994 (Box 17)
      - Cathedral Terrace, senior housing 1960-1970s (Box 17)
      - Commentary on Nicaragua-Bishop H Coleman McGehee Jr. 1986 (Box 17)
      - Creation of New Diocese Structure in southern Michigan 1994 (Box 17)
      - Crossroads Ministry, Cathedral Social Services Unit 1990s (Box 17)
      - Cursillo Weekend Retreat 1993 (Box 17)
      - Diocesan Convention Daily Newsbrief 1994 (Box 17)
      - Diocesan Staff Meetings August 1992, 1994 (Box 17)
      - Gordonwood Camp and Conference Center, Camp Holiday 1970-1980s (Box 17)
      - Latin American refugee issues and peace movements 1983-1985 (Box 17)
      - Mariners' Church, history and controversy 1969, 1976, 1985, 1990-1991 (photographs and papers) (Box 17)
      - Ministries receiving funds from Ministry with the Poor 1990 (Box 17)
      - Plan for Mutual Ministry in Northern Michigan (Upper Peninsula) undated (Box 17)
      - Pro Fide, Independent Newspaper for Michigan Episcopalians (Box 17)
      - Report Camp and Conference Planning Committee report, Gordonwood, Emrich Conference Center and Camp Chickagami (Box 17)
      - Saint Peter's Home for Boys 1994 (Box 17)
      - Sexual Misconduct Policy (draft) 1993 (Box 17)
      - The Record's Report of Diocesan Executive Council newsbriefs, 1993-1998 (Box 17)
      - Total Ministry Concept, Description and Development Guide 1982 (Box 17)
      - Tri-Diocese Meetings 1992-1994 (Box 17)
      - Trustees of the Protestant Episcopal Church for the Diocese of Michigan 1984-1985 (Box 17)
      - Urban Ministries of Episcopal Diocese of Michigan 1982, 1986 (Box 17)
      - Venture in Mission 1978-1979, 1982 (Box 17)
      - Workings of the Committee Studying Geographic Division of Michigan Diocese 1987-1988 (Box 17)
    - Photographs, 1850, 1924, 1940-1980, 1960-1980